<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<title confidence="0.99465">
A Generative Lexicon Perspective for Adjectival Modification
</title>
<author confidence="0.934686">
Patrick Saint-Dizier
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.637416">
IRIT-CNRS, Universite Paul sabatier
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.148727">
1.18 route de Narbonne F-31062 Toulouse Cedex France
</address>
<email confidence="0.213666">
stdizierOirit .fr
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.722082" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99978">
This paper presents a semantic interpretation of adjecti-
val modification in terms of the Generative Lexicon. It
highlights the elements which can be borrowed from the
GL and develops limitations and extensions. We show
how elements of the Qualia structure can be incorpo-
rated into semantic composition rules to make explicit
the semantics of the combination adjective + noun.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.983503" genericHeader="keywords">
1 Aims
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999804541666667">
Investigations within the generative perspective aim
at modelling, by means of a small number of rules,
principles and constraints, linguistic phenomena at
a high level of abstraction, level which seems to be
appropriate for research on multi-linguism and lan-
guage learning.
Among works within the generative perspect ive,
one of the most, innovative is the Generative Lexi-
con (GL) (Pustejovsky 91, 95) which introduces an
abstract model opposed to sense enumeration lexi-
cons. The GL is based (1) on the close cooperation
of three lexical semantic structures: the argument
structure, the aspectual structure and the Qualia
structure (with four roles: Telic, Agentive, Consti-
tutive and Formal), (2) on a detailed type theory and
a type coercion inference rule and (3) on a refined
theory of compositionality. The Generative Lexicon
investigates the problem of polysemy and of the null-
tiplicity of usages from a core sense of a lexeme and
shows how these usages can be analyzed in terms
of possible type shiftings w.r.t. the type expected
by the core usage. Type shifting is modelled by a
specific inference mechanism: type coercion.
In this paper, the following points are addressed:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.775066222222222">
• Generative systems require a clear analysis of
the notions of word-sense and of sense delimita-
tion. Depending on the strategy adopted (e.g.
large number or narrow senses for a lexeme as
in WordNet„ or very few but large senses as in
many Al works), the nature and the scope of
generative operations may be very different.
• The Qualia structure is a complex structure,
quite difficult to describe, in spite of evidence
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.990081083333333">
of its existence, in particular for the &amp;apos;relic role,
(explored e.g. in the EuroWordNet project, the
European WordNet). Qualias are well-designed
and useful for nouns, but look more artificial for
other lexical categories. We show that it is the
telic role of nouns which is the most useful. We
also show how the internal structure or this role
can be made more precise and its use more re-
liable and accurate by means of types and how
it can be partitioned by means of types into on-
tological domains for modelling some forms of
metaphors.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.998083967741935">
• Types are not sufficiently &amp;apos;constrained&amp;apos; to ac-
count for the constraints holding, for each
predicate, on the different sense/usage varia-
tions they may be subject, to. We show that
an underspecified Lexical Conceptual Structure
(LCS) (Jackendoff 90) is more appropriate be-
cause of its ability to represent underspecified
meaning and therefore the polymorphism of
senses in the GL, because of the relevat ice and
low-granularity of its primitives (that we have
slightly enhanced).
• Elements of the Qualia structure can be in-
corporated into semantic composition rules to
make explicit the semantics of the combination
predicate-argument, instead of developing lexi-
cal redundancy rules.
• A rule-based approach (also used by other
authors such as (Copestake and Briscoe 95),
(Ostler and Atkins 92), (Nurnberg and Zaenen
79)) is contrasted with the Qualia-based ap-
proach to deal with sense shiftings and in partic-
ular selective binding, metaphors (that the GL
cannot resolve a priori) and metonymies. An-
other view is presented in (Jackendoff 97) with
the principle of enriched composition, which is
in fact quite close to our view, but, restricted
to a few specific coercion situations (aspectual,
&amp;apos;miss-count, picture, begin-enjoy).
• The rules for type shifting we present, here are
not lexical rules, as in (Copestake and Briscoe
95), but they are part of the semantic composi-
</listItem>
<page confidence="0.987152">
1143
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998839153846154">
tion system, which makes them more general.
This paper is devoted to adjectival modification
(see also (Bouillon 97, 98)). The goal is to study
the use and impact of the Qualia structure of the
modified noun in the determination of the semantic
representation of the association Noun + Adjective.
To illustrate this study, we have chosen one of the
most polysemic French adjectives: bon (good), which
covers most of the main situations. Other adjectives,
often cited in the GL literature, such as sad, fast,
difficult or noisy have been studied and confirm tins
analysis. We observed also many similarities within
semantic families of adjectives.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.967993" genericHeader="introduction">
2 Conceptual versus Lexicographic
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.919877">
Analysis of Lexical Items
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9998504">
In this section, we outline the differences but also the
cooperation between conceptual and lexicographic
analysis of the semantics of lexical items to build
a lexicon suitable for the development of generative
devices.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.954389">
2.1 Adjectives in technical texts
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9663672">
We have considered a sample of technical texts in
French from various origins and used a simple tag-
ging and extraction system developed for our needs.
We have considered a total of 386 pages of text, with
a total of 193 1.46 word occurences, among which,
we have ii 598 occurences of adjectives. These
occurences correspond to 754 different adjectives,
among which 720 are restrictive adjectives. We will
only consider this latter set.
A srnall number of adjectives appear frequently:
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.55558">
Fig. I Adjective frequencies
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.985943428571429">
interval nb. of adjectives concerned
&amp;gt; 300 5
&amp;gt; 300 and --&amp;lt; 150 12
&amp;gt; 150 and --‹ 50 81
This means that 98 adjectives appear relatively
frequently in texts, i.e. only about 13.6% of the to-
tal. In terms of occurences, these adjectives cover
11887 occurences, i.e. about 81% of the occurences.
Adjectives from eight main &amp;apos;semantic&amp;apos; families ap-
pear frequently. These families do not correspond
exactly to those defined by (Dixon 91) (see also an
introduction in (Raskin et al. 95)), which look too
vague (figures have been rounded up or down to the
closest integer):
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.994289181818182">
Fig. 2 Adjective semantic families
Name example freq. (%)
temporal actuel, passe 10
evaluative bon, grand, cher 24
locational central, externe 10
aspectual courant, final 8
technical chimique 17
nationalities international 3
shapes rond, rectangulaire 4
society, culture econoinique, social 6
others 18
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.9991576">
In terms of (po ysemic power&amp;apos;, evaluative, loca-
tional, and shapes are the families which are the
most polysemic, with a ratio of an average of 3.8
senses per adjective. Nationalities, technical and as-
pectual adjectives are munch less polysemic.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999801">
2.2 A conceptual analysis of adjectives
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999983454545454">
The GL approach requires a conceptual analysis of
adjectives in order to focus on a relatively small
number of senses. The idea is to isolate generic con-
ceptual &amp;apos;behaviors&amp;apos;, while taking also into account
the constraints on linguistic realizations as in the
lexicographic approach.
The principle that we attempt at validating is to
define a &amp;apos;deep&amp;apos; LCS representation for each predica-
tive lexical item, which is generic enough to accomo-
date variations within a sense and precise enough to
be meaningful and discriminatory w.r.t. other word-
senses. be able to represent sense variations in an
efficient and reliable way, the variable or underspec-
ified elements should be &amp;apos;low level&amp;apos; elements such as
functions or paths. Semantic fields may also be al-
tered, e.g. going from location to psychological or
to epistemological (Pinker 93). Such an approach is
being validated on various semantic families of verbs.
The variable elements seem to belong to various
ontologies (a crucial topic under intense investiga-
tion), such as the ontology of events (active, sleep-
ing, terminated, etc.), of people&amp;apos;s quilities, etc.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999837">
2.3 Meanings of bon
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998235181818182">
In this short document, for the purpose of illustra-
tion, let us consider the adjective bon (corresponding
quite well to good), which is one of the most pol-
ysemic adjective: 25 senses identified in WordNet
(e.g. (Fellbaurn 93)). In fact, bon can be combined
with almost any noun in French, and as (Katz 66)
pointed out, good would need as many different read-
ings as there are functions for objects.
We have identified the following senses and sense
variations (metaphors and metonymies in particular,
expressed as in (Lakoff 80)):
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.665545333333333">
1. Idea of a good working of a concrete object
w.r.t. what it has been designed for: un bon
tournevis, de bons yew: (good screw-driver, good
</listItem>
<page confidence="0.982007">
1144
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.971373431818182">
eyes). Metaphors abound: e.g.: &amp;apos;communica-
tion acts as tools&amp;apos;: une bonne plaisanterie/mise
an point (a good joke), &amp;apos;function for tool&amp;apos; (un
bon odorat), &amp;apos;paths as tools&amp;apos; (a good road).
Metonymies are rather unusual since if X is a
part of Y, a good X does not entail a good Y 2.
2. Positive evaluation of moral, psychological,
physical or intellectual qualities in humans:
bonne personne, bon musicien, (good person, good
musician). The basic sense concerns professions
and related activites or humans as a whole: it
is the ability of someone to realize something
for professions, and, for humans, the high level
of their moral qualities (an enumeration can be
given or a kind of higher-order, typed expres-
sion).
This second sense could be viewed as a
large metaphor of the first, with a structure-
preserving transposition to a different ontology:
from tools to professional or moral skills.
There are some &amp;apos;light&amp;apos; metaphors such as: &amp;apos;so-
cial positions or ranks as professions&amp;apos; (a good
boss/ father /fr-iend / citizen), and a large num-
ber of metonymies: &amp;apos;image for person, image be-
ing a part of a person&amp;apos; (a good reputation), &amp;apos;tool
for profession&amp;apos; (a good scalpel), &amp;apos;place for pro-
fession&amp;apos; (a good restaurant). These metaphors
have a good degree of systematicity.
3. Intensifier of one or more properties of the noun,
producing an idea of pleasure and satisfaction
(this is different for sense 5) 3:
noun(+edible): good meal/dish/taste , tasty,
with metonymies such as &amp;apos;container for con-
tainee&amp;apos; (a good bottle/ glass),
noun ( I le- a r t ): good filin/book/paiiiting ,
valuable. with metonymies such as &amp;apos;physical
support for contents&amp;apos; (good CD),
noun(±sinelling): good odor,
noun(-1-psyclio): good relation/ experience
noun(-Flunnan relations): good neighbours.
Note that bon can only be used with neutral or
positive nouns, we indeed do not have ill French
*good ennetnies, *good humidity with the sense
outlined here.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9213395">
4. Quantification applied to measures or to quan-
tities: a good meter, a good liter, a good
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.97113194117647">
1In the combination noun -4- adjective, the noun is the
element that undergo the metaphor. The adjective being a
predicate, it is its relation to the noun it modifies which is
metaphorical, similarly to the relation verb-noun. The se-
mantics of the noun remains a priori unaltered.
&amp;apos;This needs refinements: there are some weak forms of
upward inheritance in the part-of relation: e.g. if the body of
a car is red, then the car is said to be red.
3 Norms are being defined for about 600 top-most nodes of
a general purpose ontology in different projects and research
groups (e.g. NMS11, NI, Eagles EEC project), they will be
used as soon as available.
amount/salary, a good wind. In this case, good
means a slightly more than the unit/measure
indicated or above the average (for terms which
are not measure units such as wind or salary).
This sense being quite different since it is basi-
cally a quantifier, it won&amp;apos;t, be studied hereafter.
5. Idea of exactness, accuracy, correctness,
validity, freshness, etc.: un bon raison-
neinent/calcul = exact, accurate (a good deduc-
tion/computation), good note/ticket = valid, a
good meat = fresh or eatable, a good use , ap-
propriate, good knowledge efficient, large and
of good quality. The meaning of bon is there-
fore underdetermined. Depending on the noun,
the semantics of bon is slightly different, this is
not really a case of co-composition. It is the se-
mantic type of the noun and that of the selected
predicate in the telic role of the noun which de-
termine the meaning of the adjective in this par-
ticular NP. We call this phenomenon, by com-
parison with selective binding, selective pro-
jection, because the meaning is projected front
the noun&amp;apos;s telic role. Sense 5 is substantially dif-
ferent from sense 1: it is basically boolean (e.g.
exact or not), there is no idea of tool, function
or even activity.
Bora appears in a large number of fixed or semi-fixed
forms such as: le bon goat, le bon SellS, lc bon temps,
urnc bonne giffle.
Almost, the same behavior is observed for all eval-
uative adjectives such as excellent, terrific, bad or
lousy in French. For example, for -ma-ova-ms (bad),
senses 2 and 3 are identical, sense 4 is only ap-
plicable to amounts (maimais salaire), not to units
and sense 5 is almost identical, it, conveys the idea
of erroneous deduction, invalid ticket, bad use and
rotting meat. Note that in WordNet, bad has only
14 senses, whereas good has 25 senses, with no clear
justification.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.945305">
2.4 A comparison with WordNet
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999592571428571">
We have carried out a comparison of our conceptual
analysis with the lexicographic analysis in WordNet.
We have compared manually a subset of 54 adjec-
tives among the above mentioned frequently used
adjectives. Among these adjectives, 30 are poly-
scone in our approach while 44 belong to several
synsets in WordNet:
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.895570571428571">
Fig. 3 A comparison with WordNet
criterion (1) (2)
total number of senses found 114 256
average lib. of senses/item 2.11 4.0
(1): Conceptual approach, (2) WordNet 1.6. 22
of our descriptions are close to WordNet (for adjec-
tives which are not much polysemic) while 32 differ
</figureCaption>
<page confidence="0.957023">
1145
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999682">
largely (for highly polysemic adjectives), for which
our approach identifies much less senses.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.781436">
2.5 Underspecification versus polysemy
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996749193548387">
Each of the senses of bon has many facets and inter-
pretations depending on the noun it modifies. As
for verbs or nouns (Busa 97), polymorphic types
are used to represent the semantics of the expected
nouns, viewed as arguments of the adjective predi-
cate. The semantic representation associated with
a sense is therefore underspecified and tuned to re-
flect this polymorphism. The scope of underspec-
ified elements must however be bounded and pre-
cisely defined by &amp;apos;lexical&amp;apos; types and by additional
constraints. The generative expansion of underspec-
ified fields can be defined from lexical items using a
fix-point semantics approach (Saint-llizier 96).
2.6 Towards an automatic acquisition of
conceptual descriptions
Some on-line resources and dictionaries may effi-
ciently contribute to this task. We have consid-
ered several mono- and bi-lingual dictionaries in or-
der to evaluate convergences. Only those struc-
tured on a conceptual basis are worth considering.
Among them, the Harrap&amp;apos;s German-French dictio-
nary is very nicely structured in a conceptual per-
spective, providing translations on an accurate se-
mantic basis. Senses are slightly more expanded
than in the GL approach to account for translation
variations, but, closely related senses can be grouped
to form the senses defined above.
Another source of knowledge for English is
Corelex 4, which is just being made accessible. It
contains word definitions specifically designed for
the GL. Its evaluation is about to start.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9973605" genericHeader="method">
3 Generative Devices and Semantic
Cornposition
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98573875">
Let us now analyze from a GL point of view the
meanings of the adjective bon.
In (Pustejovsky 95), to deal with the compound
adjective+noun, a predicate in the telic of the noun
is considered. For example, fast, modifying a noun
such as typist, is represented as follows:
.Xe [type&amp;apos; (e, x) A f ast(e)]
where e denotes an event. This formula says that the
event of typing is fast. A similar representation is
given for long, in a long record. This approach is ap-
propriate to represent temporal notions in a coarse-
grained way, i.e. the event is said to be fast (with
e.g. potential inferences on its expected duration)
or long. But this approach is not viable for bon, and
many other adjectives with little or no temporal di-
mension. In:
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.706031">
4 available at:
www.cs.brandeis.edu/paulb/CoreLex/corelex.html
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.993302235294118">
Ac [type&amp;apos; (e,x) A good(e)]
it is not the typing event which is &amp;apos;good&amp;apos; but the
way the typing has been performed (certainly fast,
but also with no typos, good layout, etc.). A precise
event should not be considered in isolation, but the
representation should express that, in general, some-
one types well, allowing exceptions (some average or
bad typing events). This involves a quantification,
more or less explicit, over typing events of x. Finally,
bon being polysemous, a single representation is not
sufficient to accomodate all the senses.
As introduced in section 1, the semantic represen-
tation framework we consider here is the LCS. The
nature of its primitives and its low-level granularity
seem to be appropriate for our current purpose. Un-
derdetermined structures are represented by a typed
A-calculus.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.920016">
3.1 sense 1: Bon .----=- that works well
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9994755">
This first sense applies to any noun of type tool,
machine or technique: a good car, a good screw-
driver. The semantic representation of bon requires
a predicate from the telic role of the Qualia struc-
ture of the noun. It is the set (potentially infinite)
of those predicates that characterizes the polymor-
phism. We have here a typical situation of selective
binding (Pustejovsky 91), where the representation
of the adjective is a priori largely underspecified. Let
us assume that any noun which can be modified by
bon has a telic role in which the main function(s) of
the object is described (e.g. execute programmes for
a computer, run for a car 5), then the semantics of
the compound adjective + noun can be defined as
follows:
Let N be a noun of semantic type a, and of Qualia:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.521866">
[ Telic: T, ...]
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.975432888888889">
where T denotes the set of predicates associated with
the telic role of the noun N. Let Y the variable as-
sociated with N and let us assume that T is a list of
predicates of the form Then the LCS-based
representation of bon is:
A Y : a, AF,[tat, BE+char,-Hdent ([thing Y ],
[-Fprop ABILITY —TO(h(Y,...))= high ])] .
which means that the entity denoted by the noun
works well, expressed by the evaluation function
ABILITY-TO and the value &amp;apos;high&amp;apos;. This type of
low-level function abounds in the LCS, this princi-
ple is introduced in (Jackendoff 97). Note that the
second argument of the predicate Fi does not need to
be explicit (we use the Prolog notation `_&amp;apos; for these
positions).
The Qualia allows us to introduce in a direct, way
a pragmatic or interpretative dimension via
the instanciation of
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.829709333333333">
5bess prototypical predicates can also be considered, e.g.
comfort or security for a car, which are properties probably
described in the constitutive: role of the Qualia of car.
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.993957">
1146
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.978399123595506">
The constant &amp;apos;high&amp;apos; can be replaced by a more
accurate representation, e.g. &amp;apos;above average&amp;apos;, but
the problem of evaluating a functionality remains
open. More generally, the introduction of low level
functions, such as ABILITY-TO, and specific values,
such as &amp;apos;low&amp;apos;, should be introduced in a principled
way, following the definition of ontologies of different
domains, e.g. action, intensities, etc. This is quite
challenging, but necessary for any accurate semantic
framework.
Note finally that instead of quantifying over
events, bon is described as a state: the function-
alities of the object remain good, even when it is
not used effectively. If several functionalities are at
stake, we may have a conjunction or a more complex
combination of functions
From a compositional point of view, the combina-
tion Adjective + Noun is treated as follows, where
R is the semantic representation of the adjective, T,
the contents of the telic role of the Quaint of the
noun N of type n , r, a particular element of T, and
Y, the variable associated with the noun:
sem-composition ( Adj (B.) ,Noun (Qualia(T))
: , ( Y, _) E T,
(N(Y) A II( Y )(Fi(Y, _))).
The open position in R(Y) is instanciated by
reduction. The selection of Fi is simple: kr basic
tools, there is probably only one predicate in the
Qualia (screw-driver screw), for more complex
nouns, there is an ambiguity which is reflected by
the non-deterministic choice of but probably or-
ganized with preferences, which should be added in
the Qualia. It is the constraint on the type of 17
that restricts the application of that semantic com-
position rule. This notation is particularly simple
and convenient.
Metaphors are treated in a direct way: the con-
straint on the type of Y can be enlarged to:
AY : A , mclaphor(11, a)
and the remainder of the semantic composition rule
and semantic krinula remains unchanged. We have,
for example:
metaphor(communication — act, tool) (joke).
met aphor(communication — path, tool) (road).
which is paraphrased as &amp;apos;communication path
viewed as a tool&amp;apos;.
We have evaluated that, in French, there are about
12 frequent forms of metaphors for this sense. The
study of this first sense suggests that the introduc-
tion of a hierarchy of preferences would be a useful
extension to the &amp;apos;folic role, reflecting forms of proto-
typicality among predicates.
3.2 Sense 2: Bon restricted to cognitive or
moral qualities
Another sense of bon modifies nouns of type pro-
fession or human. The treatment is the sante as
in the above section, but the selection of the pred-
icate(s) r = Fi(X ,Y) in the telic of the noun&amp;apos;s
qualia must be restricted to properties related to
the moral behavior (makes-charity, has-compassion,
has-integrity) when the noun is a person; and to
some psychological attitudes and cognitive capabil-
ities when the noun denotes a profession (e.g. a
good composer). Alternatively, some of these prop-
erties could be found in the constitutive role (ap-
proximately the part-of relation), if properties can
be parts of entities.
The typing of the predicates in the Qualia roles
can be done in two ways, (1) by means of labels iden-
tifying the different facets of a role, as in (Bergler
91) for report verbs, but these facets are often quite
ad &amp;apos;hoc and hard to define, or (2) by means of types
directly associated with each predicate. These types
can, for example, directly reflect different verb se-
mantic classes as those defined in (Levitt 93) or
(Saint-Dizier 96) on a syntactic basis, or the ma-
jor ontological classes of WordNet or EuroWordNet
and their respective subdivisions. This solution is
preferable, since it does not involve any additional
development of the Telic role, but simply the adjunc-
tion of types from a separate, pre-defined ontology.
The WordNet or EuroWordNet types also seem to
be quite easy to handle and well-adapted to the phe-
nomena we model. This remains to be validated on
a large scale.
An LCS representation for this sense of bon is, as-
suming the following types for Pi:
: human, F, : action -- related — to --
pro f cssion V moral — behavior, Y :ci,
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.4328395">
[snac B dun,,+identannuy ],
AB I L ITY — TO(Fi(Y, _)) = high ])]
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.986465529411765">
When several predicates are at stake, a set of
F1 (Y, _) can be considered in the representation, or
the statement is ambiguous.
Metonymies such as a good scalpel are resolved by
the general rule: &amp;apos;tools for professions&amp;apos;. This infor-
mation could be in a knowledge base or, alterna-
tively, it can be infered from the &amp;apos;relic role of the
tool: any instrument has a predicate in its telic role
that describes its use: the type of the first argument
of the predicate is directly related to the profession
that uses it. For example, scalpel has in its telic role:
cut(X : surgeon V biologist, Y : body).
When the profession is identified, the standard pro-
cedure for determining the meaning of the com-
pound can be applied. Metonymies using the part-of
relation are quite simple to resolve using the consti-
tutive role, as in the CL.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.59066">
3.3 Sense 3: Bon as an intensifier
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99482625">
Another main role of bon is to einphasize a quality of
the object denoted by the noun. As shown in section
2, there is a certain action associated with the telic of
the modified noun that produces a certain pleasure.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988044">
1147
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999799333333333">
For example, watching a good film entails a certain
pleasure.
Let us consider again a noun N of type a (e.g.
edible object) associated with the variable Y. The
entity (human) undergoing the pleasure is not. ex-
plicit in the NP, it is represented by X, and included
in the scope of a A-abstraction. Let Fi(X, Y) be the
predicate selected in the telic role of N. The LCS
representation is then:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.584661333333333">
AX : human, Y : a, Fi(X,Y)
[event CAUSEffevent Fi(X,Y)],
[tate BE-f-psgatiung Xi)
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.430743">
[place AT-l-5( [+p/ace pleasure ])])])].
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999104">
We have here another form of representation for bon,
where Fi is a CAUSE.
The term &amp;apos;pleasure&amp;apos; is an element of an ontology
describing e.g. mental attitudes and feelings. It is
relatively generic and can be replaced by a more pre-
cise term, via selective projection (see below for sense
5), depending on the nature of the pleasure.
An alternative representation describes a path to-
wards the value &amp;apos;pleasure&amp;apos;, giving an idea of progres-
sion:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.967254">
AX : human, Y : a, Fi(X,Y)
[event CAUSEGevent Fi(X117)1)
[event GO-Fpsy([thing X 1,
TOW ARDS+„„([+pi.„ pleasure ])])])].
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9892049">
Notice that this sense of bon does not imply an
idea of quantity: a good meal does not entail that
the meal is big, a good temperature does not entail
that the temperature is high, but rather mild. The
semantic composition rule is similar as in 3.1.
The metonymy &amp;apos;container for containee (a good
bottle) is resolved by a type shifting on Y. Y may be
of type 13 if:
3 Z : a, Y : container A container — or(1/ , Z).
Inferences are identical for e.g. a good CD.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.991348">
3.4 Sense 5: Bon = exact or correct
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.845664615384615">
We have here a. situation of selective projection: the
exact meaning of bon is projected from the type of
the modified noun and the type of the predicate se-
lected in the noun&amp;apos;s Telic role.
For example, if the noun is of type bank — note V
ticket and the type of the predicate selected in the
noun&amp;apos;s &amp;apos;relic role is pay V give — access — to, then
the meaning of bon is &amp;apos;valid&amp;apos;:
AX :bank — note V ticket,
[state BE-Echar,-Hdentathing X 1,
[place AT-Fehar,-Fident([4-propValid(X)])M.
The constraint on the type of the telic role is stated
in the semantic composition rule:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.660834">
sem-composition(Adj(R),Noun(X,Qualia(T))) =
AX : bank — note V ticket,
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9337341">
: pay V give — access — to ET,
(N(X) A n( X )
It is necessary to have both a constraint. on the
noun and on the predicate(s) in the telic role: (I)
the type of the predicate in the telic role is certainly
not a sufficient constraint , e.g. every noun&amp;apos;s telic
role in which there is the predicate pay cannot be
combined with bon with sense 5; (2) the constraint
on the type of the noun is also not sufficient, e.g. a
medecine is a kind of food, but we don&amp;apos;t eat it.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.952684" genericHeader="method">
4 Representing the core meaning of
a word-sense
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.98632996875">
The work presented here has shown the necessity of
describing the semantics of a lexical item at a rel-
atively &amp;apos;deep&amp;apos; level, in order to make explicit the
meaning elements subject to alterations in the sense.
variations shown above. It turns out, so far, that
these elements can be represented by LCS primitives
and a few functions and values, assumed to belong
to general-purpose, and often commonly-admitted,
ontologies. This remains an assumption since this
type of ontological knowledge is still under devel-
opment, but the elements used are relatively simple
and standard. Besides ontologies, and not very far
from them, we also find information contained in the
noun&amp;apos;s Qualias, but in a less structured way, making
selection more difficult.
Core meaning definition requires a good analysis
of a word-sense and of its behavior in different con-
texts. This is however not. so difficult to elaborate
once the formalism is stabilized. Also, we noted that
semantically close words share a lot, making descrip-
tions easier. This is in particular true for verbs.
Besides adjectives, we have also studied a. number
of different types of verbs, as e.g. the verb cooper
(cut), often used as an example in the literature. Its
core representation would be the following:
A I, J [event CAUSE([tnotg 1],
[event GDA( X, [path Y
with the following values for the core sense:
A = +/oc ; X = [thin, PART — 041) ]
AW AY — FROMAaplace, LOCATION — OF(
For the metaphor: &amp;apos;to cut a conversation/ a fihn,
etc...&amp;apos;, the values for the above variables become:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.985263333333333">
A = +char, +ident, X r
Levent/state
Y = AW AY — FROMAGnrop ACT IV EGO])
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.999961444444444">
where ACTIVE(J) is an elementary property of an
ontology describing the status of events. A conver-
sation is viewed as a flow which becomes non-active.
A similar treatment is observed for other types of
metaphors, with elliptic forms, such as cover Venn/
l&amp;apos;electricite/ les credits, also viewed as flows. The
property AVAILABLE(J) will then be used, which
is at a comparable abstract level in an ontology than
ACTIVE(J).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99438" genericHeader="method">
5 Long-distance compositionality
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.976217">
The NP a good meat is related to senses 2 or 5, it
therefore includes in its domain of meanings struc-
tures presented in sections 3.2 and 3.4. Instead of
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.976174">
1148
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999972413793104">
choosing one solution solution (a generate and test
strategy), a set can be provided (as in constraint
programming). Now, if we have an NP of the form:
one viande bonne a consommer, then the parsing
of consommer will provoque the selection of sense 5
(and subsense &amp;apos;fresh/consumable&amp;apos; via selective pro-
jection) because of the type of consommer. If, con-
versely, we have one viande bonne a deguster, then,
since deguster is of type &amp;apos;eat.enjoy&amp;apos; (a dotted type in
the GL), sense 2 is selected. The space of meanings
is restricted when additional information is found.
A second case involves default reasoning (as in
(Pernelle 98)). ln on bon couteau pour sculpter (a
good knife to carve), by default, the action that the
knife performs well is that protypically found in its
telic role. But, if&amp;apos; a less prototypical action is found
explicitly in the, sentence, then this latter is prefered
and incorporated into the semantic representation
instead of the default case. Indeed, the telic role
describes prototypical actions, since the others are
often unpredictable. The default meaning of bon is
kept and &amp;apos;frozen&amp;apos; until the whole sentence has been
parsed. If there is no contracdiction with that sense,
then it is assigned to the adjective, otherwise, it is
discarded in favor of the sense explicitly found in the
sentence.
Finally, we consider the expressions Y makes a
good X, Y is a good X as collocations where good is
not fully treated (-:onipositionally.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999295" genericHeader="conclusions">
6 Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999757137931034">
In this paper, we have presented an analysis of ad-
jectival modification within the GL perspective. with
the illustration of the French adjective bon. We have
proposed several extensions to the Telic role to be
able to account for the representation of the differ-
ent forms of sense variations. In particular, we have
shown how types can be added, and how predicates
from the telic participate to the construction of the
semantic representation of the compound noun +
adjective.
Coercions and the treatment of metaphors and
metonymies are generally assumed to be general
principles, however, they are in fact more specialized
than they seem at. first glance (e.g. one bonne toque/
plume a good cook/ writer is quite specific, or
very constrained). It is then necessary to introduce
narrow selectional restrictions on their use. Also,
the similarities, quite important, outlined between
the different cases presented here and observed for
other families of adjectives suggest that there is a
common typology for adjectival modification. What
then would be a general formalism ? How much are
these rules subject to linguistic variation ?
Acknowledgements I thank James Pustejovsky,
Federica Rusa aid Francoise Gayral for discussions
which helped improving this work.
I don&amp;apos;t thank my university administration, in par-
ticular the accounting dept., who made every possi-
ble effort to make this research more difficult.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.988314280701754">
II,eferences
Bugler, S., (1991) The semantics of collocational pat-
terns for reporting verbs, in proc. 5th EACL.
Bouillon, P., Mental State Adjectives: the Perspective
of Generative Lexicon, in proc. Coling&amp;apos;96, Copenhaguen,
1996.
Bouillon P., Polymorphic et semantique lexicale,
These de troisieme cycle, Universite de Paris VII, 1997.
Busa, F., (1996), Compositionality and the Seman-
tics of Nominals, PhD. Dissertation, Brandeis Univer-
sity, MA.
Copestake, A., Briscoe, T., (1995), Semi-Productive
polysenly and sense extension, journal of semantics, vol.
12-1.
Dixon, R.M. W., (1991) A new approach to English
grammar on setnantic principles, Oxford, Clarendon
Press.
Fellbaurn, C., (1993), &amp;quot;English Verbs as Semantic
Net&amp;quot;, Journal of Lexicography.
jackendoff, R., (1990), Semantic Structures, MIT
Press.
Jackendoff, R., (1997), The Architecture of the Lan-
guage Faculty, MIT Press.
Katz, G. (1966), The philosophy of Language, Harper
and Row, New-York.
Lakoff, G., Johnson, M. (1980), Metaphors we Live
By, University of Chicago Press.
Levin, B., (1993), English verb Classes and Alter-
nations: A Preliminary Investigation, Chicago Univ.
Press.
Nunberg, GD., Zaenen, A., (1992), Systematic Pol-
ysetny in Lexicology and Lexicography, proc Euralex92,
Tampere, Finland.
Ostler, N., Atkins, S., (1992), Predictable Meaning
Shifts: some lexical properties of lexical implication
rules, in J. Pustcjovsky and S. Bergler (eds.) Lexical
Semantics and Knowledge Representation, Springer Ver-
lag.
PerneIle, N., (1998), Raisonnement par dqaut et lex-
ique generatif, PhD dissertation, LIPN, Paris.
Pinker, S., (1993), Learnability and Cognition, MEI&amp;apos;
Press.
Pustejovsky, j., (1991), The Generative Lexicon,
Computational Linguistics, vol 17-4.
Pustejovsky, J., (1995), The Generative Lexicon, MIT
Press.
Raskin, V., Niremburg, S., (1995) Lexical semantics of
adjectrives, a micro-theory of adjectival meaning, MCCS
report 95-288.
Saint-Dizier, P. (1986) A Logic Programming inter-
pretation of Type Coercion Mille generative lexicon, in
proc. NLULP&amp;apos;96, Lisbon.
Saint-Dizier, P., (1996), Verb semantic classes based
on &amp;apos;alternations&amp;apos; and on WordNet-like semantic criteria:
a powerful convergence, in proc. Predicative Forms in
Natural language and in lexical knowledge bases, 1111T,
Toulouse.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996662">
1149
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.215241">
<title confidence="0.99994">A Generative Lexicon Perspective for Adjectival Modification</title>
<author confidence="0.9686195">Patrick Saint-Dizier Paul sabatier</author>
<address confidence="0.617215">1.18 route de Narbonne F-31062 Toulouse Cedex France</address>
<email confidence="0.893836">stdizierOirit.fr</email>
<abstract confidence="0.99808573015873">This paper presents a semantic interpretation of adjectival modification in terms of the Generative Lexicon. It highlights the elements which can be borrowed from the GL and develops limitations and extensions. We show how elements of the Qualia structure can be incorporated into semantic composition rules to make explicit the semantics of the combination adjective + noun. 1 Aims Investigations within the generative perspective aim at modelling, by means of a small number of rules, principles and constraints, linguistic phenomena at high level of abstraction, level which seems be appropriate for research on multi-linguism and language learning. Among works within the generative perspect ive, one of the most, innovative is the Generative Lexicon (GL) (Pustejovsky 91, 95) which introduces an abstract model opposed to sense enumeration lexicons. The GL is based (1) on the close cooperation of three lexical semantic structures: the argument structure, the aspectual structure and the Qualia structure (with four roles: Telic, Agentive, Constitutive and Formal), (2) on a detailed type theory and a type coercion inference rule and (3) on a refined theory of compositionality. The Generative Lexicon investigates the problem of polysemy and of the nulltiplicity of usages from a core sense of a lexeme and shows how these usages can be analyzed in terms of possible type shiftings w.r.t. the type expected by the core usage. Type shifting is modelled by a specific inference mechanism: type coercion. In this paper, the following points are addressed: • Generative systems require a clear analysis of the notions of word-sense and of sense delimitation. Depending on the strategy adopted (e.g. number senses for a lexeme as in WordNet„ or very few but large senses as in Al works), the nature and scope generative operations may be very different. • The Qualia structure is a complex structure, quite difficult to describe, in spite of evidence its existence, particular for the &amp;apos;relic role, in the EuroWordNet project, the European WordNet). Qualias are well-designed and useful for nouns, but look more artificial for other lexical categories. We show that it is the telic role of nouns which is the most useful. We show how the internal structure role can be made more precise and its use more reliable and accurate by means of types and how it can be partitioned by means of types into ontological domains for modelling some forms of metaphors. • Types are not sufficiently &amp;apos;constrained&amp;apos; to account for the constraints holding, for each predicate, on the different sense/usage variations they may be subject, to. We show that an underspecified Lexical Conceptual Structure (LCS) (Jackendoff 90) is more appropriate because of its ability to represent underspecified meaning and therefore the polymorphism of senses in the GL, because of the relevat ice and low-granularity of its primitives (that we have slightly enhanced). • Elements of the Qualia structure can be incorporated into semantic composition rules to make explicit the semantics of the combination predicate-argument, instead of developing lexical redundancy rules. • A rule-based approach (also used by other authors such as (Copestake and Briscoe 95), (Ostler and Atkins 92), (Nurnberg and Zaenen 79)) is contrasted with the Qualia-based approach to deal with sense shiftings and in particular selective binding, metaphors (that the GL cannot resolve a priori) and metonymies. Another view is presented in (Jackendoff 97) with of enriched composition, is in fact quite close to our view, but, restricted to a few specific coercion situations (aspectual, &amp;apos;miss-count, picture, begin-enjoy). • The rules for type shifting we present, here are not lexical rules, as in (Copestake and Briscoe but they are part of the semantic composi- 1143 tion system, which makes them more general. This paper is devoted to adjectival modification (see also (Bouillon 97, 98)). The goal is to study the use and impact of the Qualia structure of the modified noun in the determination of the semantic representation of the association Noun + Adjective. To illustrate this study, we have chosen one of the polysemic French adjectives: which covers most of the main situations. Other adjectives, cited in the GL literature, such as fast, been studied and confirm tins analysis. We observed also many similarities within semantic families of adjectives. 2 Conceptual versus Lexicographic Analysis of Lexical Items In this section, we outline the differences but also the cooperation between conceptual and lexicographic analysis of the semantics of lexical items to build a lexicon suitable for the development of generative devices. in technical texts have a sample of technical texts in French from various origins and used a simple tagging and extraction system developed for our needs. have considered a total of 386 pages with a total of 193 1.46 word occurences, among which, we have ii 598 occurences of adjectives. These occurences correspond to 754 different adjectives, among which 720 are restrictive adjectives. We will this latter set. A srnall number of adjectives appear frequently: Fig. I Adjective frequencies interval nb. of adjectives concerned &amp;gt; 300 5 &amp;gt; 300 and --&amp;lt; 150 12 &amp;gt; 150 and --‹ 50 81 means that adjectives appear relatively frequently in texts, i.e. only about 13.6% of the toterms of occurences, these adjectives cover 11887 occurences, i.e. about 81% of the occurences.</abstract>
<note confidence="0.538055333333333">Adjectives from eight main &amp;apos;semantic&amp;apos; families appear frequently. These families do not correspond those by (Dixon 91) (see also an</note>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<pages>II,eferences</pages>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>II,eferences</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Bugler</author>
</authors>
<title>The semantics of collocational patterns for reporting verbs,</title>
<date>1991</date>
<booktitle>in proc. 5th EACL.</booktitle>
<marker>Bugler, 1991</marker>
<rawString>Bugler, S., (1991) The semantics of collocational patterns for reporting verbs, in proc. 5th EACL.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Bouillon</author>
</authors>
<title>Mental State Adjectives: the Perspective of Generative Lexicon,</title>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>in proc. Coling&amp;apos;96, Copenhaguen,</booktitle>
<marker>Bouillon, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Bouillon, P., Mental State Adjectives: the Perspective of Generative Lexicon, in proc. Coling&amp;apos;96, Copenhaguen, 1996.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Bouillon</author>
</authors>
<title>Polymorphic et semantique lexicale, These de troisieme cycle, Universite de Paris VII,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<marker>Bouillon, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Bouillon P., Polymorphic et semantique lexicale, These de troisieme cycle, Universite de Paris VII, 1997.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F Busa</author>
</authors>
<title>Compositionality and the Semantics of Nominals,</title>
<date>1996</date>
<location>PhD. Dissertation, Brandeis University, MA.</location>
<marker>Busa, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Busa, F., (1996), Compositionality and the Semantics of Nominals, PhD. Dissertation, Brandeis University, MA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Copestake</author>
<author>T Briscoe</author>
</authors>
<title>Semi-Productive polysenly and sense extension, journal of semantics,</title>
<date>1995</date>
<volume>vol.</volume>
<pages>12--1</pages>
<marker>Copestake, Briscoe, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Copestake, A., Briscoe, T., (1995), Semi-Productive polysenly and sense extension, journal of semantics, vol. 12-1.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R M W Dixon</author>
</authors>
<title>A new approach to English grammar on setnantic principles,</title>
<date>1991</date>
<publisher>Press.</publisher>
<location>Oxford, Clarendon</location>
<marker>Dixon, 1991</marker>
<rawString>Dixon, R.M. W., (1991) A new approach to English grammar on setnantic principles, Oxford, Clarendon Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Fellbaurn</author>
</authors>
<title>English Verbs as Semantic Net&amp;quot;,</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Journal of Lexicography.</journal>
<marker>Fellbaurn, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Fellbaurn, C., (1993), &amp;quot;English Verbs as Semantic Net&amp;quot;, Journal of Lexicography.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R jackendoff</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantic Structures,</title>
<date>1990</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<marker>jackendoff, 1990</marker>
<rawString>jackendoff, R., (1990), Semantic Structures, MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R Jackendoff</author>
</authors>
<title>The Architecture of the Language Faculty,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<marker>Jackendoff, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Jackendoff, R., (1997), The Architecture of the Language Faculty, MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Katz</author>
</authors>
<title>The philosophy of Language,</title>
<date>1966</date>
<location>Harper and Row, New-York.</location>
<marker>Katz, 1966</marker>
<rawString>Katz, G. (1966), The philosophy of Language, Harper and Row, New-York.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Lakoff</author>
<author>M Johnson</author>
</authors>
<title>Metaphors we Live By,</title>
<date>1980</date>
<publisher>University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
<marker>Lakoff, Johnson, 1980</marker>
<rawString>Lakoff, G., Johnson, M. (1980), Metaphors we Live By, University of Chicago Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Levin</author>
</authors>
<title>English verb Classes and Alternations: A Preliminary Investigation,</title>
<date>1993</date>
<publisher>Univ. Press.</publisher>
<location>Chicago</location>
<marker>Levin, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Levin, B., (1993), English verb Classes and Alternations: A Preliminary Investigation, Chicago Univ. Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>GD Nunberg</author>
<author>A Zaenen</author>
</authors>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>Systematic Polysetny in Lexicology and Lexicography, proc Euralex92,</booktitle>
<location>Tampere, Finland.</location>
<marker>Nunberg, Zaenen, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Nunberg, GD., Zaenen, A., (1992), Systematic Polysetny in Lexicology and Lexicography, proc Euralex92, Tampere, Finland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N Ostler</author>
<author>S Atkins</author>
</authors>
<title>Predictable Meaning Shifts: some lexical properties of lexical implication rules,</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>Lexical Semantics and Knowledge Representation,</booktitle>
<editor>in J. Pustcjovsky and S. Bergler (eds.)</editor>
<publisher>Springer Verlag.</publisher>
<marker>Ostler, Atkins, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Ostler, N., Atkins, S., (1992), Predictable Meaning Shifts: some lexical properties of lexical implication rules, in J. Pustcjovsky and S. Bergler (eds.) Lexical Semantics and Knowledge Representation, Springer Verlag.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N PerneIle</author>
</authors>
<title>Raisonnement par dqaut et lexique generatif,</title>
<date>1998</date>
<location>LIPN, Paris.</location>
<note>PhD dissertation,</note>
<marker>PerneIle, 1998</marker>
<rawString>PerneIle, N., (1998), Raisonnement par dqaut et lexique generatif, PhD dissertation, LIPN, Paris.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Pinker</author>
</authors>
<title>Learnability and Cognition,</title>
<date>1993</date>
<publisher>MEI&amp;apos; Press.</publisher>
<marker>Pinker, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Pinker, S., (1993), Learnability and Cognition, MEI&amp;apos; Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>j Pustejovsky</author>
</authors>
<date>1991</date>
<journal>The Generative Lexicon, Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>vol</volume>
<pages>17--4</pages>
<marker>Pustejovsky, 1991</marker>
<rawString>Pustejovsky, j., (1991), The Generative Lexicon, Computational Linguistics, vol 17-4.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Pustejovsky</author>
</authors>
<title>The Generative Lexicon,</title>
<date>1995</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<marker>Pustejovsky, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Pustejovsky, J., (1995), The Generative Lexicon, MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V Raskin</author>
<author>S Niremburg</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexical semantics of adjectrives, a micro-theory of adjectival meaning,</title>
<date>1995</date>
<journal>MCCS report</journal>
<pages>95--288</pages>
<marker>Raskin, Niremburg, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Raskin, V., Niremburg, S., (1995) Lexical semantics of adjectrives, a micro-theory of adjectival meaning, MCCS report 95-288.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Saint-Dizier</author>
</authors>
<title>A Logic Programming interpretation of Type Coercion Mille generative lexicon,</title>
<date>1986</date>
<booktitle>in proc. NLULP&amp;apos;96,</booktitle>
<location>Lisbon.</location>
<marker>Saint-Dizier, 1986</marker>
<rawString>Saint-Dizier, P. (1986) A Logic Programming interpretation of Type Coercion Mille generative lexicon, in proc. NLULP&amp;apos;96, Lisbon.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Saint-Dizier</author>
</authors>
<title>Verb semantic classes based on &amp;apos;alternations&amp;apos; and on WordNet-like semantic criteria:</title>
<date>1996</date>
<marker>Saint-Dizier, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Saint-Dizier, P., (1996), Verb semantic classes based on &amp;apos;alternations&amp;apos; and on WordNet-like semantic criteria:</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>a powerful convergence, in proc.</title>
<booktitle>Predicative Forms in Natural language and in lexical knowledge bases, 1111T,</booktitle>
<location>Toulouse.</location>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>a powerful convergence, in proc. Predicative Forms in Natural language and in lexical knowledge bases, 1111T, Toulouse.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>